It's time to make our skiing character look more like the actual skiing and less like their driving,
because right now our character just moves left and right, sort of similar to our car.
However, what we want is it for to be able to almost glide as if you were in the snow?
Meaning if we move to the left and then let go of our arrow keys, it should keep sliding for a bit,
whereas at the moment our character just stops.
So how can we achieve this more dynamic and smooth turning motion?
And at first there may seem like there is no obvious answer here.
You may be thinking to use this glide block here, but you can only glide to a specific position and
can't just change your position with a gliding motion.
However, programming is all about problem solving using the tools we have, and one of those tools
are variables.
And here there are a lot of things that variables can do.
So let's see how we can use them to our advantage.
So let's create a variable and we will call it movement direction.
Now moving back to our script here, let's remove this change x by in the if statement and drag one
of them into the forever loop.
I know this seems strange, but bear with me.
Then drag this movement direction into the change x by.
Now.
Finally, if the right arrow is clicked, I want to change the movement direction by one.
And if the left arrow is clicked, I want to change the movement direction by minus one.
And I hope this is starting to make sense to you now, because basically what is happening in the script
is our character is always moving in the direction of this variable, and the value of this variable
is determined by the if we click the left or the right arrow.
So let's give this a test.
So as you can see, when we click to the left or right before our movement direction table goes up down,
down.
So as you can see out, this movement is a smoother.
And I'm doing a lot more like active two.
However, there's a problem you might notice, and that's if we let go of our keys after turning, our
player just keeps drifting off into the direction it was going, which is definitely not ideal.
So to fix this, we need a way for our variables to automatically return to zero.
And you may be thinking, ah, I will just stick this inside of our else block and well testing that
you'll see.
If we ski to the left and let go.
Well, that's a bit harsh.
Also, you'll notice that if we ski to the right, it almost goes in slow motion.
And well, that is just because our if script is badly set up.
Because if you look at it, we have an if else statement and an if statement below it, which is never
something you should do as the else should always be the last in the conditional check.
So let's fix this mistake now.
And to fix this, all we need to do is grab another if else block, then stick this code inside.
Get rid of the if statement and then finally put all this code inside our if else.
So now if you look at it, you can see that our else is the final condition.
And if we play, it doesn't go in slow motion, although we still have the same harsh stopping problem.
But before we fix that, let's quickly fix this other script.
As you can see, we made the same mistake here.
Much I think, and much I feel clean code folders is.
So now let's fix the last problem of our character just stopping when we let go.
So the first thing we can do is get rid of this set movement direction to zero.
And here we need a way for it to slowly bring our variable back to zero.
And the best way to do this is by using our old friend mathematics, but thankfully not the hard type.
So we're going to need some more if checks.
So let's first grab one more of these if else blocks and one if block.
We will put the first one inside here and the second one inside this one okay.
So for this first if then block, we basically want to check if our movement direction is already zero.
And if it is we don't want to do anything more.
So to do this we're going to grab a few blocks here which are the two movement direction variables and
greater than.
Elicit an and an or block so we can connect all these all together.
Just like that.
And here we want to check if our movement direction is greater than 0.1 and less than -0.1.
And what this is doing is basically checking our movement direction is not equal to zero.
So we can put this in our first if condition.
And now to the next one.
So simply we can just duplicate this here, stick it inside our if statement and set it to zero.
So basically now if movement direction is less than zero, we want to change movement by a positive
number to slowly bring it back.
So let's say 0.2.
And then finally, in this else statement, we can change movement direction by -0.2.
And yet this may all seem a bit confusing, but if you look at it as a whole, it's not so confusing.
So go through it from the top.
Basically, we are first detecting if our sprite is moving.
If it is, then we want to slow it down.
So if it is moving to the left we slow it down by increasing this number.
Otherwise, if it is moving to the right we decrease this number.
So that's pretty much it.
So let's give it a go.
Skiing left and right is working.
Well, then, letting go of our keys.
As you can see, our player slowly comes to a stop.
Perfect.
So now we can hide our movement direction variables as it's all working.
That's the end of this lesson, and I know it might have been a confusing one.
So what I want you to do now is just really take a good look at the script to better understand it.
Also play around with it, change a few values and see what happens.
Because this is what learning is all about.
You can always press the magic button, command Z or control Z to undo what you did.
So play undo, play undo until you have it figured out.